Finding Aid for M Wwomen publications, 1980-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
M Women publications 1980-1998
University of Michigan. Michigan Women’s Athletic Association
0.2 linear foot
97118 Bimu 2
Volunteer organization dedicated to the support and growth of women's varsity athletics at the University of Michigan, founded in 1979. Publications include annual reports, brochures, directories, and newsletters entitled M Women, M Women Newsletter, and the University of Michigan Women's Athletic Association Newsletter
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor # 8586 ) and Sheryl Szady (donor # 7769 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publications are open to research.
Prior to the passage of Title IX in 1972, women's sports did not enjoy varsity status nationally. This legislation was passed in an effort to end this and other discriminatory practices at schools that received federal funds. Two examples of the types of discrimination that occurred were that men had varsity athletics and women did not and men had funding and scholarships available and women did not. When Title IX was passed the University of Michigan chose seven women's club sports to elevate to varsity sport status for the 1973-74 school year; these included: tennis, basketball, swimming, diving, synchronized swimming, volleyball and field hockey. Women who participated in these varsity sports at the University of Michigan were eligible for the block "M" athletic letter in 1974. Men who received letters also became members of the M Club (a men's social club). The M Club had no female athletes among its members. The idea for a women's club for female athletes, similar to that of the M Club, was proposed in 1978. The Michigan Women's Athletic Association "M-Women" was founded in 1979. The group began its meetings in 1980 with Helen Morsink as its first president. The mission statement of the organization is to "promote, foster, and assist in the growth and promotion of the University of Michigan's women's athletic programs." The group became dedicated to helping fund female athletes by providing fellowships and scholarships to student athletes and their coaches. Membership to the M-Women is open to both fans and athletes, male or female.
The Unit Publications series includes annual reports entitled President's Annual Report, brochures, directories, and invitations. The newsletters were first published in September 1980 under the title The University of Michigan Women's Athletic Association Newsletter. It continued under this title until June 1982. In December 1982 the title changed to M Women Newsletter. Publication under this title continued at least until Spring/Summer 1986. The Bentley Library holds issues of a third newsletter M Women from Winter 1988 through the present.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Michigan Women's Athletic Association.; M women.; M women newsletter.; University of Michigan women's athletic association newsletter.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Directories.; Newsletters.
- Unit Publications
  - Annual Reports (Box 1)
    - President's Annual Report, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Membership Directory, 1994, 1998, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - M Women, 1988-2006, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - M Women Newsletter, 1982-1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Women's Athletic Association Newsletter, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
  - Website, 1999-2001 (Box 1)